Guide to the John Mihelic Collection MS 015
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
John Mihelic Collection
1908-1927, (Bulk 1918-1924)
1918-1924
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Mihelic, John
MS 015
3.5 Linear Feet, 2 boxes and 1 OS folder
John Mihelic was from Kansas City, Missouri and was a member of the Socialist Party. He was also involved with the Communist Party of America. The collection includes some correspondence and leftist/socialist publications from the early 20th century.
Provenance
Harriette Tax (niece of Thelma Fogel), Professor Emeritus of the School of Professional Studies, donated the Mihelic collection to the Archives and Special Collections Department of the Ruth Haas Library.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
John Mihelic was born on February 2, 1898 in Kansas City, MO to John and Matilda Mihelic. Milhelic finished High School in Kansas City and then spent time "riding the rails." In his travels in the late 20s, he met a Russian-born woman Thelma Fogel who had moved with her family to St. Louis in 1921. The two lived together for 10 years and married in 1941. In addition to running a book store near the University of Chicago from 1940-1970, Mihelic also found work as a business machine repair man. Mihelic died on April 21, 1980.
Between 1919 and 1926, he was an active member of the Socialist Party. He was also involved with the Communist Party of America.
The "2nd National Convention" of the Communist Party of America was held at Bridgman, MI, August 17-22, 1922. It was prematurely terminated for fear of police action. On Aug. 22, a police raid did occur and 17 members of the CPA were arrested including Mihelic. Members of the CPA who were arrested at the Bridgman convention include: Phillip Aronberg, Alex Bail, Eugene Bechtold, Earl R. Browder, William F. Dunne, Charles Erickson, William Z. Foster, Alex Georgian, Caleb Harrison, Charles Krumbein, Cyril Lambkin, Max Lerner, Elmer McMillin, John Mihelic, Seth Nordlind, Thomas J. O'Flaherty, William Reynolds, C.E. Ruthenberg, A. Severino, T.R. Sullivan, Norman H. Tallentire, and Joseph Zack [Kornfeder].
Sources:
The Communist Party of America (1919-1946) [http://www.marxists.org/history/usa/eam/cpa/communistparty.html]
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of this collection consists of political booklets and periodicals published by individuals and organizations active in labor movements across the country, and reflect communist and socialist viewpoints on many topics. Many of the booklets discuss trials, unlawful searches and seizures, raids, and arrests without due process of law. The booklets are arranged alphabetically and span the years 1908-1927.
The correspondence files contain very little information pertaining to Mihelic's direct involvement with the Socialist Party. Several letters indicate he corresponded directly to William Haywood, the Secretary-Treasurer of the General Defense Committee, and traveled to union meetings in order to raise funds for the Defense Committee.
Also included in the correspondence file are 17 pages (carbon copies) of labor history in poem and lyric form some of which were set to well known music. In 1915, Ralph Chaplin, a poet and writer and organizer for the Industrial Workers of the World, wrote Solidarity Forever to the tune of Battle Hymn of the Republic. These lyrics and song later became the anthem of the American labor movement.
Of particular interest is a letter of introduction for Mihelic signed by William Z. (Zig Zag) Foster, a U. S. labor leader and a member of the American Socialist Party. Foster was a union organizer, leader of the 1919 U. S. Steel strike, and founding member and leader of the American Communist Party. He was also the presidential candidate for the Communist Party in 1924, 1928, and 1932, and chairman of the American Communist Party after World War II (box 1, folder 2).
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 2 series.
Kansas City (Mo.); Haymarket Square.; Lumber trade -- - Washington (State).; United States -- Politics and government.; Fliers (printed matter); Working class -- United States -- History -- 20th century; World War, 1914-1918 -- Periodicals; Booklets; Socialism -- United States.; Publications.; Correspondence.; Labor songs and poetry.; Labor -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Socialism -- Europe.; Socialism -- Periodicals.; Communism -- United States -- Periodicals.; Communist trials -- United States.; Employee rights -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Labor movement -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Anarchists -- United States; Communism -- Europe.; Communism -- Periodicals.; Communism -- United States.; Lasovsky, A. (S. A. Dridzo); Industrial Workers Of The World.; Haywood, William D.; Hard, William.; Hanson, Nils H.; Gold, Michael.; Gitlow, Benjamin.; Gildea, Charles; George, Harrison; Ferguson, Isaac E.; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Chaplin, Ralph, 1887-1961; Centralia, 1919; Cannon, James P.; Bukharin, N.; Minor, Robert.; Trade Union Educational League.; Varney, Harold Lord.; Vorse, Mary Heaton.; War Information Series.; Riebe, Ernst.; Roberts, John Emerson; Ruthenberg, C. E.; Socialist Workers Party.; Owen, George E.; Parsons, Lucy E.; Radek, Karl; Ramirez, J.
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1919-1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1919-1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Booklets
  - Agriculture. The World's Basic Industry and Its Workers., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bukharin, N. Program of the Communists (Bolshevists)., ca.1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Burns's and Daugherty's Attack Upon Labor and Liberty., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Burns's and Daugherty's Attack Upon Labor and Liberty. (c.2), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cannon, James P. The Fifth Year of the Russian Revolution., undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chaplin, Ralph. The Centralia Conspiracy., 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A Communist Trial. Extracts from the testimony of C. E. Ruthenberg and closing address to the jury by Isaac E. Ferguson, ca.1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Contribution Forms - Defense Fund, undated (Map-case OS Drawer 3, Folder *)
  - De Leon, Daniel. The Burning Question of Trades Unionism. A Lecture Delivered at Newark, N. J. on April 2, 1914., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Descriptive Catalog. (4 copies), 1921 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - George, Harrison. Is Freedom Dead?, ca.1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gildea, Charles. Corruptionists and Union Wreckers., undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gold, Michael and Ramirez, J., Proletarian Song Book of Lyrics from the Operetta 'The Last Revolution.', undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hanson, Nils H. The Onward Sweep of the Machine Process., undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Industrial Democracy. Address delivered by Hon. Glenn E. Plumb, President of the Plumb Pan League to the Sixteenth Convention of the International Association of Machinists. Rochester, New York. September 24, 1920. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - International Socialist Review, 1909-1917 (Box 1, Folder 18-21)
  - Kansas City Guide & Union Station Time Table v. 2; December 1915. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Labor Herald., 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 23-30)
  - The Labor Herald., 1924 (Box 2, Folder 31-34)
  - Losovsky, A. (S. A. Dridzo.) The International Council of Trade and Industrial Unions., ca.1920 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Losovsky (Dridzo), A., The Role of the Labor Unions in the Russian Revolution., 1920 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Manifesto and Program, Constitution, Report to the Communist International., undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Greater New York., 1919 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Metropolitan"Bolshevist Russia. Raymond Robins' Story told to William Hard." June-October 1919. (Map-case OS Drawer 3, Folder *)
  - Minor, Robert. Stedman's Red Raid., 1921 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - More Truth About the I. W. W., ca.1918 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - The One Big Union Monthly. March 1, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Owen, George E. Authority., ca.1908 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Owen, George E. Authority. (c. 2), ca.1908 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Radek, Karl. Is the Russian Revolution a Bourgeois Revolution?, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - The 'Red Ruby', Address to the Jury by Benjamin Gitlow; Also Darrow The Judge Giovanitti., undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Riebe, Ernest. Crimes of the Bolsheviki., 1919 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Riebe, Ernest. Crimes of the Bolsheviki. (c. 2), 1919 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Roberts, John Emerson. The Struggle of a Mind to be Free., 1917 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Ruthenberg, C. E. Why Every Worker Should Be a Communist and Jointhe Workers Party., undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - The Silent Defense. A Story of the Remarkable Trial of Members of theIndustrial Workers of the World Held at Sacramento, California., ca.1917 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - '"The Communists in the United States, The Michigan Communist Case January 1923." (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - The Social Service Bulletin. Testimony of William D. Haywood before the Industrial Relations Commission., 1915 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Theses and Statutes of the Third (Communist) International., 1920 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Eleventh of November Memorial Edition. November 11, 1887-1912. (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Varney, Harold Lord. Industrial Communism-The I. W. W., undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Vorse, Mary Heaton. The Passaic Textile Strike 1926-1927., undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - The War for Peace. War Information Series, March 1918. (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Photographs, 26 images, undated (Box 2, Folder 58-59)
  - Miscellaneous: 4 x 6 Sketch of Vladimir Lenin (framed)., undated (Map-case OS Drawer 3, Folder *)